Stephen E. Malawista papers
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
- Lyme disease files, Part 1 (open), Series VI
  - Popular articles on Lyme disease written or corrected by Malawista, Subseries 2
    - Draft of "Fundamental aspects of Rheumatology," for Current Rheumatology, 1984 (Box 48, Folder 15)
      The article summarizes the symposium, "Fundamental Aspects of Rheumatology," held in Stockholm, Sweden. Malawista was asked for any changes to the summary of his presentation and for illustrations.
    - Article on Lyme disease for Dermatology Times, 1988 (Box 48, Folder 16)
      Sent by the editors for Malawista's correction. Folder contains cover letter and Malawista's ample edits.
    - "The treatment of Lyme disease," for The Medical Letter, 1988 July (Box 48, Folder 17)
      Malawista's note on this copy states that the article was written by Robert Schoen and himself and reviewed by Joseph Craft, Allen Steere, and [illegible].
    - S. E. Malawista, "Statement on Lyme Disease" for ACR, 1989, February 20 (Box 48, Folder 18)
      Malawista sent this "statement" to Shaun Ruddy, Chairman, Research Council, ACR.
    - Article on Malawista's ACR talk for Rheumatology News, 1990 (Box 48, Folder 19)
      Malawista was sent "a pre-publication copy of a report on your recent lecture on Lyme disease at the ACP Annual Session" for use in Rheumatology News. The report was to be published in February 1991.
    - S.E. Malawista, "Update on Lyme Disease," American College of Physicians, 1990 April 27 (Box 48, Folder 20)
      Two copies of typed information, possibly a handout at the American College of Physicians meeting, Chicago, April 27, 1990.
    - ACR, Draft of "Policy Statement on Antibiotic Therapy for 'Possible' Lyme Disease", ca. 1990 (Box 48, Folder 21)
      Daniel Rahn of Yale was one of the authors of this typescript.
    - "Literature File Update" for Today in Medicine, 1991 (Box 48, Folder 22)
      The format of this piece was a question and answer on "Third-generation cephalosporins in in the treatment of Lyme disease." Malawista insisted that his name not be used.
    - Article on Malawista's work for International Medical News Service, 1991 (Box 48, Folder 23)
    - "The Treatment of Lyme Disease" for The Medical Letter, 1992 August 25 (Box 48, Folder 24)
      Malawista was asked by the editor to review the proposed article. Folder contains correspondence, text of the draft article, and Malawista's comments on the draft.
    - Bob Shope, Draft of "Lyme disease", 1993 August 31 (Box 48, Folder 25)
      Bob Shope, Department of Epidemiology and Public Health at Yale, asked Malawista to look over the text and help him update the 16th edition of Control of Communicable Diseases in Man.
    - Draft of "Treatment of Lyme Disease" for The Medical Letter, 1997 March 21 (Box 48, Folder 26)
    - Article on Lyme disease for Lyme Disease Research Update, 1997 (Box 48, Folder 27)
      The writer of the article thanked Malawista for his corrections and sent the revised version. The article quotes from an interview with Malawista.
    - Jonathan A. Edlow, book proposal on a history of Lyme disease, 1999-2002 (Box 48, Folder 28)
      Correspondence of Yale University Press and Dr. Jonathan Edlow concerning the manuscript of his history of Lyme disease, originally called "Shadows in the Lymelight." On request from the press, Malawista evaluated the proposal in 1999. The book was published as Bull's-eye: Unravelling the Medical Mystery of Lyme Disease. New Haven: Yale University Press, 2003, 2nd ed. 2004.
  - Malawista and Lyme disease -- miscellaneous, Subseries 3
    - Site visit to Yale by an NIH Study Section for presentations on Lyme arthritis, 1977 April 27 (Box 48, Folder 29)
      The study section was "General Medicine A." The talks were by Malawista, Steere, Hardin, Shope, Wallis, and McCollum. Folder contains the agenda, Allen Steere's CV, and copies of maps and data.
    - List of articles on Lyme disease by Allen Steere, ca. 1985 (Box 48, Folder 30)
      Includes a handout for Grand Rounds, 1983.
    - List of articles on Lyme disease by Stephen Malawista, ca. 1993 (Box 48, Folder 31)
    - Literature surveys by Malawista and Ruth Montgomery, ca. 1988-1991 (Box 48, Folder 32)
    - Malawista correspondence on the Lyme Borreliosis Foundation, 1990 July 30-August 7 (Box 48, Folder 33)
      The Lyme Borreliosis Foundation, Tolland, Connecticut, headed by Karen Vanderhoof-Forschner, was a patient advocacy group, which often differed from Lyme researchers such as Malawista. The particular subject here was a paper given by Eliot Frank, M.D., at the Fourth Annual Conference of Lyme Borreliosis, to which Vanderhoof-Forschner strongly objected and sent a letter to Frank's superior at the Jersey Shore Medical Center. Malawista wrote on behalf of Frank.
    - S. 2839: "Lyme Disease Research and Education Act of 1990" (Box 48, Folder 34)
      This U.S. Senate bill was introduced by Connecticut Senator Joseph Lieberman.
    - Materials for an early talk on Lyme arthritis, 1970s (Box 48, Folder 35)
      Most of Malawista's presentations on Lyme disease can be found in Series 9, "Talks and Travels." These next folders contain materials not related to specific talks.
    - Notes and slides for a talk on Lyme disease, 1983 (Box 48, Folder 36)
    - Lyme Disease presentation slides, circa 1988-2013 (Box 48, Folder 37)
    - Miscellaneous materials Malawista used in talks, ca. 1989-1992 (Box 46, Folder 38)
      These were found in multiple copies. An example is a quote from Rev. Billy Graham mentioning Lyme disease.
    - Lyme-related arthritis slides, circa 1990-2013 (Box 48, Folder 39)
    - Numbered slides used in a talk on Lyme disease, 1998 August (Box 48, Folder 40)
  - Newspaper clippings on Lyme Disease, Subseries 4
    Clippings from the New York Times, New Haven Register, and other newspapers. Sometimes there is a note with the clipping on who sent it to Malawista. Clippings were mixed with other materials in Malawista's Lyme Disease files. Arrangement by year is by the archivist.
    - Clippings on Lyme Arthritis, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 1)
    - Clippings on Lyme Arthritis, 1977 (Box 49, Folder 2)
    - Clippings on Lyme Arthritis, 1978 (Box 49, Folder 3)
    - Clippings on Lyme Disease, 1979 (Box 49, Folder 4)
    - Clippings on Lyme Disease, 1980-1982 (Box 49, Folder 5)
    - Clippings on Lyme Disease, 1983-1984 (Box 49, Folder 6)
    - Clippings on Lyme Disease, 1985-1986 (Box 49, Folder 7)
    - Clippings on Lyme Disease, 1987-1988 (Box 49, Folder 8)
    - Clippings on Lyme Disease, 1989-1990 (Box 49, Folder 9)
    - Clippings on Lyme Disease, 1991 (Box 49, Folder 10)
    - Clippings on Lyme Disease, 1992-1993 (Box 49, Folder 11)
    - Clippings on Lyme Disease, 1994 (Box 49, Folder 12)
    - Clippings on Lyme Disease, 2000-2013 (Box 49, Folder 13)
    - Clippings on Lyme Disease, no date (Box 49, Folder 14)
  - Popular materials on Lyme Disease, Subseries 5
    Includes clippings from issues of newsletters of professional societies as well as general articles from popular and scientific journals; pamphlets for the public, etc.
    - Popular materials on Lyme Arthritis, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 15)
    - Popular materials on Lyme Arthritis, 1977 (Box 49, Folder 16)
    - Popular materials on Lyme Arthritis, 1978 (Box 49, Folder 17)
    - Popular materials on Lyme Disease, 1979 (Box 46, Folder 18)
    - Popular materials on Lyme Disease, 1980-1981 (Box 49, Folder 19)
    - Popular materials on Lyme Disease, 1982-1984 (Box 49, Folder 20)
    - Popular materials on Lyme Disease, 1985-1987 (Box 49, Folder 21)
      Includes Gerald Weissmann, "Daumier and the Deer Tick," Hospital Practice (May 15, 1989), 181-200, on Malawista and Steere.
    - Popular materials on Lyme Disease, 1988 (Box 49, Folder 22)
    - Popular materials on Lyme Disease, 1989 (Box 49, Folder 23)
    - Popular materials on Lyme Disease, 1990 (Box 50, Folder 1)
      Folders from here on also contain publications from patient advocacy groups who opposed medical scientists such as Malawista concerning the diagnosis and treatment of Lyme disease.
    - Popular materials on Lyme Disease, 1991 (Box 50, Folder 2)
    - Popular materials on Lyme Disease, 1992 (Box 50, Folder 3)
    - Popular materials on Lyme Disease, 1993 (Box 50, Folder 4)
    - Popular materials on Lyme Disease, 1994-2006 (Box 50, Folder 5)
    - Popular materials on Lyme Disease, no date (Box 50, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters on Lyme Disease, including patient advocacy groups, Subseries 6
    - Centers for Disease Control, Center for Infectious Diseases, Lyme Disease Surveillance Summary, 1991-1994 (Box 50, Folder 7)
    - Lyme Borreliosis Newsletter, 1986-1988 (Box 50, Folder 8)
      Edited by Dr. A, G. Barbour, Rocky Mountain Laboratories, Hamilton, Montana, and Dr. G. Stanek, Hygiene Institute of the University of Vienna, and printed by BIOCHEMIE GesmbH, Vienna.
    - Lyme Borreliosis Foundation, ca. 1988-1991 (Box 50, Folder 9)
      The Lyme Borreliosis Foundation, Tolland, CT, was a patient advocacy group headed by Karen Vanderhoof-Forschner. Folder contains miscellaneous mailings.
    - Lyme Disease Update, 1991-1992 (Box 50, Folder 10)
      Published by Charlene Glover, Mills Shoals, Illinois, for Lyme disease patients.
    - Lyme Disease Update, 1993-1994 (Box 50, Folder 11)
  - Research articles by others on Lyme Disease, Subseries 7
    This section contains reprints and other copies of research articles on Lyme disease that Malawista saved. Other than on Lyme disease, reprints by others in Malawista's files have not been retained.
    - Articles on Lyme Disease, 1922, 1967, 1974, 1977 (Box 50, Folder 12)
      These are articles before the announcement of Lyme arthritis that in retrospect might be relevant. The 1922 article in French was on paralysis by ticks.
    - Articles on Lyme Disease, 1978-1982 (Box 50, Folder 13)
    - Articles on Lyme Disease, 1983 (Box 50, Folder 14)
    - Articles on Lyme Disease, 1984 (Box 50, Folder 15)
    - Articles on Lyme Disease, 1985 (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - Articles on Lyme Disease, 1986-1988 (Box 51, Folder 2)
    - Articles on Lyme Disease, 1989-1990 (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - Articles on Lyme Disease, 1991-1992 (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - Articles on Lyme Disease, 1993-2007 (Box 51, Folder 5)
    - Companies advertising products related to Lyme disease, 1988 and no date (Box 51, Folder 6)
      Advertisements for the FIAX Lyme Disease Test Kit by Whitaker Bioproducts, Inc, 1988; and for Damminix for control of Lyme disease carrying ticks, by EcoHealth, Inc.
- Lyme disease files, Part 2 (restricted), Series VII
  These files were separated out by the archivist because they contain information on named patients and are therefore restricted. Please consult with the Librarian for Medical History.
  - Correspondence on Lyme Disease, Subseries 1
    Restricted access. This correspondence was found scattered in Malawista's Lyme Disease files. Some of it is from individuals who believe they or a relative have contracted Lyme disease. Files thus contain individually identifiable medical information.
    - Correspondence on Lyme arthritis, 1976 (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence on Lyme arthritis, 1977 (Box 52, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence on Lyme arthritis, 1978 (Box 52, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence on Lyme disease, 1979-1985 (Box 52, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence on Lyme Disease, 1986-1993 (Box 52, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence on a Lyme disease patient in Connecticut, 1997-1998 (Box 52, Folder 6)
    - Letters to Yale School of Medicine requesting testing of ticks that bit people, ca. 1994-1997 (Box 52, Folder 7)
      One example of tick in a plastic bag included (probably the wrong size tick). Letters given numbers for testing.
    - Correspondence on Lyme disease, 2001- and no date (Box 52, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence concerning studies of cases of Lyme disease in Europe, 1981-1985 (Box 52, Folder 9)
      Concerns work with Charles Mackworth-Young, Tufts University School of Medicine, and colleagues in France. Contains information on named patients.
    - Correspondence about a patient in San Francisco, 1986 (Box 52, Folder 10)
      Case in which the patient's physician consulted with Malawista.
    - Correspondence about a patient in Oregon, 1993 (Box 52, Folder 11)
  - Research and patient data, Subseries 2
    - Lyme disease patient data, 1976 (Box 52, Folder 12)
    - Personal story about Lyme disease by a collaborator of Malawista, 1983 May 1 (Box 52, Folder 13)
    - "Lyme Specimen Bank" - test results, 1983-1993 (Box 52, Folder 14)
      Named patients tested by Robert T. Schoen, M.D.
    - Yale Lyme Research Group meeting, 1988 December 7 (Box 52, Folder 15)
      Minutes discuss various strategies for using animal models for the eventual discovery of a vaccine.
    - "Study of Fifth Disease (Parovirus B19 Infection), Masquerading as Lyme Disease," patient surveys, 1989 (Box 52, Folder 16)
      See Articles 101, 1992.
    - Daniel W. Rahn, Case notes on a Lyme patient, 1989-1990 (Box 52, Folder 17)
      Notes taken each time the named patient saw Dr. Rahn.
    - Research with Soren Nielsen and James B. Peters, Specialty Laboratories, Inc., on a test for Lyme disease, 1989-1990 (Box 53, Folder 1)
      Malawista was collaborating with Nielsen and Peters, Specialty Laboratories, Inc., Santa Monica, California, sending samples (CSF) from Lyme patients to test the ability of "PCR to permit the specific identification of B. burgdorferi DNA in fluids and tissues." Joint efforts led to an abstract: Soren L. Niesen, James B. Peter, Robert T. Schoen, Daniel W. Rahn, and Stephen E. Malawista, "B. burgdorferi Persistently Detected by PCR in Synovial Fluid of a Patient with Lyme Disease Resistant to Therapy," December 1989. Soren and Peter did not collaborate on any paper in Malawista's CV. File contains patient information.
    - Research with Soren Nielsen, Specialty Laboratories, Inc., 1990 (Box 53, Folder 2)
      Soren L. Nielson was the first author of an article "Detection of Borrelia DNA by the polymerase chain reaction," Molecular and Cellular Probes, 4 (1990): 73-74. Included in folder.
    - "ECP Photopheresis Study", 1989-1990 (Box 53, Folder 3)
      Questionnaire and patient names and data.
    - CETUS Corporation collaboration on Lyme disease, 1989-1990 (Box 53, Folder 4)
      Malawista had been in contact with Dr. Ann Begovitch on a collaboration concerning the clinical course of Lyme disease. This agreement was likely not signed.
    - Patient data and research, 1989-1990 (Box 53, Folder 5)
      May contain materials from several studies.
    - Lyme patient X., 1989-1992 (Box 53, Folder 6)
      Named patient with chronic Lyme disease.
    - Patient X's Lyme spirochete DNA, 1993 (Box 53, Folder 7)
      Includes 2 computer disks, printouts, and other information.
    - Pfizer Azithromycin study led by Daniel W. Rahn, M.D., 1990 (Box 53, Folder 8)
      The study was intended to test Azithromycin, manufactured by Pfizer, in the treatment of early Lyme disease.
    - Study on the use of polymerase chain reaction (PCR) to diagnose Lyme disease, 1990-1991 (Box 53, Folder 9)
    - Patient data and research, 1991 (Box 53, Folder 10)
      Material in this file and similar files was brought together by the archivist and may refer to several different studies.
    - "Early Lyme Study" - Erythema migrans - patient data, 1992 (Box 53, Folder 11)
      Contains survey forms on named people bitten by ticks and their associated symptoms. This folder may relate to folder 8.
    - Patient data and research, 1992 (Box 53, Folder 12)
    - Patient data and research, 1993 (Box 53, Folder 13)
    - Mouse protection study, 1994 (Box 53, Folder 14)
      Mice injected with human sera. Some patient names.
- Lyme Vaccine Study (restricted), Series VIII
  This study, led by Malawista working with Janine Evans, M.D., was funded by Connaught Laboratories to test a vaccine that Connaught Laboratories had developed. The official title was "Efficacy Study of a Lyme Vaccine." This is a separate study from the SmithKline Beecham vaccine study also conducted at Yale.
  - Protocols, Subseries 1
    Protocol folders sometimes include the reporting of "adverse" events to named participants in the studies.
    - Protocol 7404 correspondence, 1993-1996 (Box 54, Folder 1)
      Correspondence concerning the protocol for "Efficacy Testing of Lyme Vaccine," a study in partnership with Connaught Laboratories. Included is Yale University, Human Investigations Committee, Guidelines (1993).
    - Protocol 7404 "Efficacy Testing of a Lyme Vaccine", 1993-1996 (Box 54, Folder 2)
      Folder contains protocol, 1994; Human Investigation Committee Guidelines, 1993; and a report of an adverse reaction without the person's name.
    - Protocol U93-4700-03, Connaught Laboratories, 1993-1994 (Box 54, Folder 3)
      Protocol for "Efficacy Testing of a Lyme Vaccine" from the Connaught Laboratories' side. Also includes the "Patient Information and Consent Form," 1993, which states "The vaccine to be tested is a single purified protein of the Lyme disease bacteria, made in bacteria by recombinant DNA technology similar to the technology used to produce the Hepatitis B vaccine."
    - Protocol 8130 "Efficacy Study of a Lyme Disease Booster", 1995-1998 (Box 54, Folder 4)
    - Protocol U93-4703-03/05, Connaught Laboratories, 1998-2001 (Box 54, Folder 5)
  - Vaccine trials, Subseries 2
    - Lyme Disease Vaccine Study, 1993-1994 (Box 54, Folder 6)
      Includes Yale Medical News announcement of the study and correspondence with Connaught Laboratories, Inc., and Yale administrators.
    - Lyme Disease Vaccine Study, 1995-1996 (Box 54, Folder 7)
    - Lyme Disease Vaccine Study, 1996-1997 (Box 54, Folder 8)
    - Agreement with Pasteur Merieux Connaught USA, 1998-2000 (Box 54, Folder 9)
      Study titled "Safety and Immunogenicity of an Accelerated Schedule of the OspA Vaccine for Lyme Disease." The company, by then named Aventis Pasteur, Inc., informed Malawista on January 14, 2000, of its decision to stop work on the vaccine.
    - Correspondence with a patient who participated in the vaccine study, 2000 (Box 54, Folder 10)
      Participant said the vaccine worked and sent a picture of his leg where the tick bit him.
    - Erol Fikrig, Lyme Disease Vaccine Study, 2004-2005 (Box 54, Folder 11)
      This study, in which Malawista was involved, was "Immune Responses in Individuals who have Previously Received the OspA Lyme Disease Vaccine Series." Folder includes protocols.
  - Expenses, Subseries 3
    - Expenses for Lyme Vaccine Study/Marketing, 1993 December-1994 February (Box 54, Folder 12)
      Includes the ways in which the study was advertised to obtain participants. Contains names of patients in the study.
    - Expenses for Lyme Vaccine Study/Marketing, 1993 December-1994 February (Box 54, Folder 13)
    - Expenses for Lyme Vaccine Study/Marketing, 1997-1999 (Box 54, Folder 14)
- Talks and Travel ("T/T"), Series IX
  This series was maintained by Malawista's successive secretaries who created files for talks away from Yale and for professional meetings. Sometimes folders were created for events Malawista probably didn't attend. Additional material on talks and meetings was found loose in Malawista's papers and added by the archivist to "T/T." Folders may contain correspondence, programs, announcements, abstracts of papers that Malawista and his colleagues presented, texts of talks, and occasional photographs.
  - 1950s
    - "Cirrhosis of the Liver", 1957, 1964 (Box 55, Folder 1)
      Malawista explained in a note to Gerald Klatskin at Yale in 1964 that he was an organizer of the Columbia-Presbyterian Medical History Society and had presented this historical talk in 1957.
  - 1960s
    - American Society for Clinical Investigation, Atlantic City, 1962 April (Box 55, Folder 2)
      J. E. Seegmiller, R. Rodney Howell, and S. E. Malawista, "A Mechanism of Action of Colchicine in Acute Gouty Arthritis," presented at the American Society for Clinical Investigation, Atlantic City, April 1962. Abstract in J. Clin. Invest. 41: 1939, 1962.
      Drafts of abstract and paper.
    - American Rheumatism Association, Chicago, 1962 June (Box 55, Folder 3)
      The presentation was S.E. Malawista, R. Rodney Howell and J.E. Seegmiller, "Factors Modifying the Inflammatory Response to Injected Microcrystalline Sodium Urate." Malawista notes that the presentation was "Not on program." Abstract in this folder was published in Arthr. Rheum. 5: 307, 1962. The folder also includes another abstract by Howell and Seegmiller; S.E. Malawista, "Discussion of paper by James S. Faires and Daniel J. McCarty, ARA meeting, Chicago, June 21, 1962; and a copy of the abstract of the paper discussed.
    - Third Pan-American Congress on Rheumatic Diseases, Santiago, Chile, 1963 October 15-19 (Box 55, Folder 4)
      "Colchicine in Acute Gouty Arthritis: Clinical and Metabolic Studies," 1963. Paper presented by Stephen Malawista on behalf of himself, R. Rodney Hopwell, and Jay Seegmiller, at the Third Pan-American Congress on Rheumatic Diseases, Santiago, Chile, October 15-19, 1963. Folder contains correspondence, 1963, paper and abstract, memorabilia, and photographs of Malawista and other participants at the Congress
    - Abstract rejected for presentation by the American Society for Clinical Investigation, 1964 February (Box 55, Folder 5)
      S. E. Malawista, "Sols, gels, and the mechanism of action of colchicine," rejected in February 1964 for presentation at the meeting of the American Society for Clinical Investigation, 1964. Abstract published in in. J. Cl. Invest, 43: 1241, 1964.
      Correspondence rejecting the abstract for presentation, and drafts. Malawista would have been introduced by Paul Beeson.
    - American Rheumatism Association, 1964 June 19 (Box 55, Folder 6)
      S. E. Malawista, "Sols, gels and colchicine: a common formulation for the effects of colchicine in gouty inflammation and on cell division," presented at the ARA meeting on June 19, 1964. Abstract published in Arthr. Rheum. 7: 325, 1964.
      Correspondence including a letter from Alvan Feinstein to the ARA, abstract, and drafts.
    - Interurban Clinical Club, New Haven, 1964 December 4 (Box 55, Folder 7)
      Malawista's presentation at the meeting was "Mechanism of Action of Colchicine on Gouty Inflammation."
      Folder contains drafts and printed program of meeting.
    - Presentations, Woods Hole, Mass., 1965 Summer (Box 55, Folder 8)
    - XI International Congress of Rheumatology, Mar Del Plata, Argentina, 1965 December 5-11 (Box 55, Folder 9)
      S.E. Malawista and Phyllis Bodel, "Dissociation by colchicine of phagocytosis per se from increased oxygen consumption in inflammation in human leukocytes: Implications in gouty inflammation," presented at XI International Congress of Rheumatology, Mar Del Plata, Argentina, December 5-11, 1965. Abstract published in the Proc. XIth Internat. Cong. of Rheum., December, 1965.
    - XI International Congress of Rheumatology, Buenos Aires, 1965 December 8 (Box 55, Folder 10)
    - Dermatology Research Group, Atlantic City, 1966 April 30 (Box 55, Folder 11)
      Malawista presented the paper he had offered to present at the American Federation for Clinical Investigation meeting. See next folder.
    - American Federation for Clinical Investigation, Atlantic City, 1966 May 1-4 (Box 55, Folder 12)
      Proposed paper was "Potentiation of the Colchicine Effect of Frog Melanocytes by High Hydrostatic Pressure." Paper rejected but presented at another meeting. See previous folder.
    - Society for Clinical Investigation, 1966 May 2 (Box 55, Folder 13)